<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the King with some observations upon the two houses / by a true son of the Church of England, and a lover of his countries liberty.  Together with the resolution of Wiltshire, and the petition of the gentlemen of the foure Innes of Court,</title>
            <author>Waller, Edmund, 1606-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08251134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08251134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1243:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the King with some observations upon the two houses / by a true son of the Church of England, and a lover of his countries liberty.  Together with the resolution of Wiltshire, and the petition of the gentlemen of the foure Innes of Court,</title>
                  <author>Waller, Edmund, 1606-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Webb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Pamphlets.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Pamphlets.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE KING, WITH Some OBSERVATIONS upon the <hi>TWO HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES:</hi> By a true Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a lover of his Countries Liberty.</p>
            <p>Together with the Reſolution of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and the Petition of the Gentlemen of the foure <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> in behalfe of all the true Proteſtants in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> His MAjESTIES Letter to both Houſes of PARLIAMENT the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for WILLIAM WEBB, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41188:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41188:2"/>
            <head>A Vindication of the <hi>KING,</hi> with ſome Obſervations upon the two <hi>HOUSES,</hi> by a true Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and a Lover of his Countries Liberty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not be curious to ſatisfie the Reaſon of any prepoſſeſt opinion, yet ſince the Times hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an open Preſſe to cleare every imagination which is not ſtifled in this Dampe. I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to contract my owne Meditations in a narrow roome, and rather expoſe them to the cenſure of the moſt judicious, then reſt ſatisfied alone, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this cloudy ſurface to overwhelme ſo vaſt a body.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe it was no meane part of my happineſſe in our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous extreames, to hope for a happy Union by that ſoveraigne medicine of a fading State, a Parliament; and knowing the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable affection of our gracious Soveraigne to the peace and quiet of the Kingdoms, though it was His unſpeakable misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, never to know the miſery of the people, till their diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents were grown to that head, they became almoſt (if not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together) uncurable, by thoſe unreaſonable and illegall Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, exacted by ſome ill-affected agents, conducing little to his advantage; but to the furthering of their ambition, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding could as eaſily deſert him in his miſery, as before be the ready Inſtruments to importune him to this miſchief, upon pretence of a Legall Authority: which who knows not a Prince may be ſoon miſtaken in, ſince none can be ſo filly as to beleeve
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41188:3"/>him a ſtudied Lawyer: Yet that this ſhould expoſe us to ſo great an adventure, as not onely to diveſt him of this ſuſpected Arbitrary power, but to conferre an abſolute Government to any whatſoever, renders me no other axiom then the Poets,
<q>Incidit in Scyllam cupiens vitare Carybdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</q> But if you pleaſe to take the true ſtate of the buſineſſe, let your impartiall Judgement confer with your Reaſon upon theſe few notorious truths. What has the King denied which concerne our Liberty, and are the undoubted ſecurities of our happineſſe under the Regiment of a juſt and unqueſtionable Monarchy?</p>
            <p>Are not our Rights and Properties already eſtabliſht this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by ſuch Acts of Grace, as could never finde Preſidents from His Anceſtors? beſides the utter extirpation of Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Monopolies, upon what pretence ſoever thoſe Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Courts of Juſtice, High-Commiſſion, Starre-Chamber, Marſhal-ſeas, &amp;c. Has He not importuned the ſetling of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in its purity, and that there might be a Law to ſecure the tender conſciences of thoſe who will not agree to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? Are not the taking away theſe ſufficient ground to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve our Jealouſies, if ever we meant to be ſatisfied? As for their feares, I wiſh we had as little reaſon to ſuſpect the fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as we have the King; who is ſo clearely diveſted of any power, to make good the leaſt injuſtice, that it's too great an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard on His part, to adventure what our conſciences enforce us to make good for Him on our part; &amp; the conſervation of theſe are ſo atteſted by Him (in the word of a King) with ſuch unuſual expreſſions, that if they came from a Stranger, (I ſuſpected not an Infidell) I was bound to beleeve in charity? Witneſſe thoſe ſerious aſſeverations, <hi>God ſo deale with Me and my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as I intend to conſerve my Parliament in it's Priviledges, the Rights of the Subjects, and the true profeſt Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, God ſo proſper me in what I take in hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there yet a further way to eſtabliſh them, whereby they may be ſo ſecure, that a violation may ſeeme impoſſible, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſubverſion of the very Letter of the Law? Why is it not propos'd if it be no Invaſion of that juſt Prerogative, was never denied His Anceſtors? and what He hath deſerved of us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41188:3"/>that he may not be as far truſted, is as hard to object as eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. If then we muſt needs agree that there being nothing ſo cleare, why ſhould any ſubtle pretences hinder our deſired accommodation, unleſſe there be ſuch that intend the alteration of our Government? and how inconſiſtent that may prove to a People already managed under the united Order of a virtuous King, daily experience offers it too eaſie of conjecture. Yet for our better ſatisfaction, let's weigh the amends wee are like to make our ſelves from theſe few inconveniences, amongſt the thouſands which daily expoſe themſelves to our view.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The unlimited power of the two Houſes hath already aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed into their own hands a formall Ordinance, countermand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuſpending, nay, creating Acts of Parliament, though not in the name of Acts, yet in the power of Acts, whereby both King and People are obliged to obey; how to diſtinguiſh this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from an Act of State, I am not well ſatisfied; yet I have heard it call'd Treaſon in one of their Members for this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, though with that cautious proviſoe, That it ſhould be no leading caſe to future ages for Judges to imitate. Is this the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of our undoubted Rights we have ſo long endeavoured? who carries not now his life in his hand, mannag'd by an exact power of a bare Vote, which if any contradicts, muſt ſuffer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of a Malignant party, though of their own Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and not proceeded againſt by the juſtice of any precedent Acts, but condemned by the Votes of the preſent Seſſion: and if this be not an abſolute ſubverſion of the Rights of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deſtructive to the fundamentall Lawes of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (wherein our Liberty conſiſts) I would faine be ſatisfied what it is: for 'tis moſt apparent to whoſoever examines their ordinary proceedings, we have no Law left but what ſerves their turne; and if that be defective to puniſh thoſe they pleaſe to call Delinquents, their Legiſlative Ordinance can as well ſupply that defect, as it could make that obnoxious, which till this Parliament no man could ever call a fault.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This continuing power of the two Houſes, which if they had had a minde ſhould ever bee remitted, they would have either expreſſed it in their firſt demand, and limited it to a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41188:4"/>certain time, wherein they might have compleatly qualified the diſquiet countenance of a troubled Eſtate; or ſince have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured ſome Remonſtrance for our ſatisfaction in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: For I would faine be anſwered, Firſt, if they ſit while they liſt, and paſſe what they liſt, whether they have not (dureing their pleaſure) ſubverted our Monarchy by their Democracy, and inveſted themſelves with a power more Arbitrary then the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall Government could pretend to; that having his Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Rules of Law, which the Judges are to anſwer (if they miſtake) or thoſe that adviſe the King: their Democracy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no bounds, being but a thing of yeſterday, and which as yet we cannot underſtand, aſſuming to themſelves the ſole power to judge of our dangers, and to propoſe ſuch remedy as may anſwer their pretences.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How every conſcientious man can diſpence with that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oath of Allegiance, wherein he calls God to witneſſe for the vindication of his Princes juſt Prerogative, and their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation to maintain an abſolute and unlimited power in the two Houſes, wreſted to thoſe Ordinances expreſly inhibited by His Majeſties ſpeciall commands: in my underſtanding it is to no other purpoſe then to leade us into a Maze, where, when we are loſt by our miſunderſtanding (which muſt neceſſarily be the principall of our ſubverſion,) They will offer us a Clue, ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leade us to their premeditated deſignes, whereby of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity they will become our Maſters; or to an inevitable ruine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we know the reaſon of our Feares and Jealouſies, being the old rule they ſo often enveighed againſt: Firſt, to trouble the State, then to ſubvert the Government. Let it not be objected now, That I am againſt Parliaments, for (God knowes) I am for them; and as zealous for my Country as any man that lives: But in my opinion, the beſt way to ſecure our Liberty had been, That our Members of both Houſes might continue ſubject ſtill, lyable to the Regiment of thoſe Lawes which ſhall be enacted by them; wherein they will have a care of ſecuring their owne eſtates for the future, as well as ours, which was certainly the intentions of our well adviſed Anceſtors, in expoſing ſo great a truſt into their hands, when the Prince called for their advice in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41188:4"/>matters of greateſt concernment; but by this continued Seſſion, they not onely are inveſted with an abſolute power, but are able to make themſelves amends at leiſure for thoſe monies exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted out of their eſtates, while we groane under the inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burthen of their (as they call them) Legall Taxes; and thus they may well be careleſſe what Lawes are paſt, never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be obſervers, but Lords of what they make.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Who are theſe pretended Reformers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but the very Inſtruments who were the favourites du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our oppreſſion? I need not name them to any, who has once attended the Epidemicke trouble of our age, and what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of converſion we can make of their lives, whereby ſuch a confidence ſhould be repoſed in them, as to deveſt ſo Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Juſt a Prince of his unqueſtionable Rights and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and conferre ſuch an unlimited power ſo readily upon them, if we return to our former ſenſes, renders me amazed; 'tis not amiſſe to ruminate ſome words His Majeſtie uſed in His owne vindication at <hi>Newmarket:</hi> My Lords, lay your hands on your hearts, who were the contrivers of theſe illegall Taxes, wherewith you have ſo incenſed my people? to whoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage were theſe impoſitions levied? are my Exchequers at all larger, or did they not rather conduce to your peculiar benefit? who were the onely perſwaders of them, that you have now repaid me with condigne thankes? Thoſe Favourites being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be the cauſers, though not companions of their Princes miſ-fortunes, being like Crowes upon a carkaſſe, that have no ſooner bared the bones but they are flowne; are we not yet ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, the rules of policy, not of honeſty, to ſecure their lives and fortunes, not their conſciences, expoſed you to this poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, not publique ſervice? and had you not in ſo exact a courſe ſerved your turnes of theſe loyall pretenders, they had beene as lyable to the extremity of Juſtice as the greateſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, that under-went the moſt heavy cenſures; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly had had their deſerved ſhares, which would have given a better colour to their upright proceedings, as they would have you ſo believed, if they had impartially diſtributed Juſtice amongſt the then Malignant party: But now that we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41188:5"/>ſhould be ſo ſtupid as to be circumvented with any pretences whatſoever, which out-ſtrip the Eſſentiall rules of Government or Reaſon, and confide in the poſitive Vote of an ambitious par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for ought we know, would admit my perſwader to be a mad man that could allow that in his opinion. But make them what you will, ſuppoſe them to be the moſt reall and upright men in their lives and conſciences in the whole world, They are but the Counſell of the King and Kingdome, not their Commanders; for the health of our State is admirably ballanced, if that have but its due proportion: The Parliament conſiſting of three bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the King, the Lords and Commons; ſo that if two ſhould be deſtructive, and the third remaine ſound, during thoſe Laws already in force, there can be no danger to our Kingdome; but if either of the two can paſſe at their pleaſure what they will, the third muſt then of neceſſity ſtand for a Cypher, for conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or diſagreeing is then of equall value, and in my opinion it's a preſident of too great an adventure; for ſuppoſe the King and the major part of the Lords ſhould agree an Ordinance or Law, we ſhould think it extreamly prejudiciall to the Liberty of the Subject, our Commons ſhould be concluded peremptorily againſt their conſents. I heard an Act not long ſince vouched in preſident, that had beene ratified againſt the conſent of the Lords Spirituall, where they declared <hi>nec poſſumus, nee volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus conſentire;</hi> and this ſo rare wee could not finde a ſecond. At the Parliament at <hi>Oxford</hi> in 17. <hi>H.</hi> 3. when the Lords were not there preſent, they were faine to diſſolve the Houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſing one Act, confirming my firſt propoſition, That the conſent of two bodies are not of force to make us Lawes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the third, much leſſe conclude. The King, who is not only the ſupreame head, but the very ſoule, whoſe power gives life to their actions, when their body is once diſſolved; beſides, how incoherent is it with that authority committed to them? for if the Parliament (which are onely his great Councell) offer him a Bill, which He is bound to agree unto, it was more then ever His Anceſtors were; and of his Counſellors, it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow they are His Commanders.</p>
            <p>We have a Maxime with the Subject, <hi>Modu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; conventio
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41188:5"/>vincunt legem:</hi> In former ages, and ever ſince Parliaments were in uſe, <hi>Le Roy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aviſera</hi> were ſufficient authority to make a Bill of both Houſes unwarrantable; and how the King hath loſt that Right, or what new Laws are found out deſtructive to that Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, I never yet read, nor ever ſhall, unleſſe ſome ſuch new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or bare Votes can pretend to ſuch an unwarranted power, (whereof there was never yet found a Preſident) which can have no other operation upon my underſtanding, then, That the Votes of the preſent Members which can at their pleaſures diſpoſe the undoubted Priviledges of the Crowne (by a Law recorded onely in their owne breaſts) and giving out to us, under the guilded Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Peoples Liberty, when indeed they are but Golden Chaines inſtead of Bulruſhes, and (reſerv'd till occaſion ſhall make it too apparent) may finde out a Law of equall force to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Crowne, when they ſhall ſo farre debilitate the Prince, as he ſhall be no way able to make reſiſtance; for when the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters are not onely undermined, but clearly taken away, by what reaſon can we imagine the Structure may continue firme? that you may be ſure we will not unjuſtly charge them, be pleaſed to obſerve with me their Orders in theſe few inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their countenancing theſe unwarranted Acts, either by a ſeditious huddle of indigent people, and ſo procuring Petitions to neceſſitate theſe premeditated proceedings, or leavying an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Warre againſt the King; ſecuring us upon no other reaſons then that they are the repreſentative body of the Kingdome, and therefore our Obedience rather to be expected, then our Reaſon ſatisfied, which indeed is true enough, if they proceeded upon that warranted rule to which no man could refuſe obſervance, or being intruſted by Us with the power of preceding Parliaments; that they would purſue points of ſo high concernment, with the ſame mature reaſons and deliberations, as they have done, and then they might well expect our readineſſe to ſecure their actions. But ſuppoſe we elect one that ſhould ſpeak or endeavour to enact Treaſon, does our election bid us to ſecure him, or will future Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments blame us hereafter for giving up ſo great a Delinquent to the juſtice of the Lawes? dare we countenance their Intentions, who have fetcht Preſidents from the weakeſt Princes, (nay, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41188:6"/>go beyond them too) to the diſadvantage of as able a Prince as ever yet held the Scepter; nay, and offer their ſuppoſitions to the Vulgar, If the Prince be a foole, a child, &amp;c. ought he not to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by his Councell, though it be againſt his conſent, if it ſtand with the publike benefit: what implication to make of this I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, but I am ſure that it was none of our meaning when we gave our voyce in the Election? Can an Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without the conſent of the King, renew a repealed Act, and with ſo bold a countenance trample upon the heeles of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds time, and this very repealed Act renewed this Parliament, be within one ſtep of it, wherein the Parliament tooke the Crowne, and gave it to the then Earle of <hi>Bullingbrooke;</hi> which was the reaſon of ſo much bloud in our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warres, and was not well ſettled till of late yeares? And can we blame the King if He deſire ſhelter from ſuch a ſtorme: If it be their intentions, ſure one <hi>Bullingbrooke</hi> will not ſerve their turnes, ſince there hath beene equall ſhares in this ſo great an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture. And to vouch the Oath of this Uſurper <hi>H.</hi> 4. which came in at their benevolence to a Prince of an unqueſtionable Title, and never offered before or ſince to any Engliſh King that ever we read or heard of (but with its limitations) is ſo far from their loyall pretences, that they are rather to be believed ſtudied miſchiefes, and endeavours, to embroyle the Kingdome in a Civill Warre.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To diſingage all that would out of affection, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove, intereſt themſelves to ſecure the Kings Perſon and Dignity (it being too apparent to any ordinary underſtanding) that ſuch proceedings were never warranted by any precidents of preceding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or thoſe Lawes they call fundamentall in our Kingdome, they ſcandalize ſuch with the name of malignant Perſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by His Meniall Servants, either abſolutely refuſed, or durſt not adventure His attendance, and countenance this medley in ſuch a ſenſe, that the King Himſelfe is perpetually traduc'd under this obſtruſe Dialect; which though they dare not put down in plaine Engliſh, for feare the moſt violent amongſt them ſhould be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to owne it: yet by ſuch an implication, as the plaineſt capacity cannot but bluſh, and with admiration wonder, whereto this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41188:6"/>may tend, I would faine be ſatisfied what theſe might not doe, when they had once maſtered theſe their malignants: For if you will give us as much reaſon as the Ants, you muſt beleeve a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may come, as well as thinke a Summer is come: durſt any man then oppoſe their proceedings, when they have reduced all to their owne Termes; do you not ſpeak your ſelves the very Law, and we as we ought to yeeld no appeale from Parliament, being the higheſt Court in the Kingdome; yet in this ſenſe as the King is a part of it, (for otherwiſe I underſtand not by what right) it has the preheminence of thoſe they call the Kings Courts, being both conveen'd by the ſame Royall Authority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The diſcountenancing any Petitions whatſoever, (wherein we deſire to interpoſe our advice for accommodation, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) though never ſo agreeing with our Lawes, unleſſe they ſtand with the ſence of their party, as if all our Wiſedome were ſhut up in ſo narrow limits, and theſe the onely men in <hi>England</hi> infallible: yet give me leave to averre, That to the number of almoſt two hundred approved able men, whoſe warranted judgement and ſufficiencies were the onely inducement of their Countries Election, have beene faine to ſit ſtill, and ſee things carried in this diſorderly confuſion, (peremptorily againſt their earneſt endeavours) and have not beene ſo much as askt their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in matters of greateſt concernment; but being unwilling to expoſe their Conſciences to ſo high a Guilt, have withdrawne themſelves as unuſefull Members of ſuch a Body.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To inſinuate a beliefe of their care to the Vulgar, They have perpetually ſurmiſed terrible Jealouſies, which have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced no other effect then a deſired ſuſpition of the King; yet theſe offered upon moſt improbable conjectures, as every private Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſufficient grounds to piece up their deſignes, or by ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe private diſcontents leade them to offer theſe high indignities to that ſacred Perſon, they were never worthy to ſerve in the meaneſt Office; and though their Lives were ſo notorious for their former extravagancies, they have by theſe ſuperfluous invectives found countenance, till preſuming upon their merits, which were none, except to abuſe the King, can be called deſert; That they have beene given up to rapine, or ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41188:7"/>ſuch damnable ſinne, that nature would never have pardoned, if we had had no Law; Yet theſe mens informations, ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ground to traduce the King, theſe Letters moſt neceſſary Animadverſions to leavy Forces, to maintain the Kings Forts, Towns, &amp; Magazines againſt Him; I, &amp; in His own name too, as if they could derive that authority from Him, that has no power (according to your Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) to leavie them in His owne Defence, though His Perſon is in never ſo apparent imminent danger; yet they for His good, and the good of the Kingdome, can pretend to this power, and beyond: yet that all is not of that infallibility, let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Pyms</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> witneſſe with me.</p>
            <p>I have committed theſe few Obſervations, to the view of the Publique, finding ſo many bold Pamphlets (with ſo high impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) fly at the Face of Majeſty unreproved, and every corner ſtinks of this uncleane Doctrine; yet ſince it is come to this height, that we muſt declare our ſelves, or looſe our King: wherin my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe failes, my life ſhall make good to my laſt breath; but if Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Reaſon, and Law had not warranted ſo juſt a cauſe, I ſhould never have adventured to cleare a glaſſe to ſo foule a countenance: yet before I conclude, let mee propoſe one queſtion in Religion: Whether the Church was not in it's purity in the Primitive times? the World agrees they had in thoſe dayes a King that was no Chriſtian? Whether Chriſt had not more power (then ever any can or dare pretend to ſince) to eclipſe that Regall Dignity if it had beene deſtructive to the Church? yet hee refuſed the loweſt office of a Magiſtrate, <hi>But gave to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that were His;</hi> for when the young man came to him, and ſaid, <hi>Lord command my brother that he divide the Inheritance with mee:</hi> He replyes, <hi>Who made mee a Ruler, or a judge amongſt you?</hi> But now that we having a Chriſtian King, profeſſing by His unblemiſht Life, the ſame way to ſalvation with us, proteſting to conſerve our Liberties with His Life, to make ſuch an apparant difference, which may be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the effuſion of ſo much Chriſtian Bloud, upon meere Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, will be the moſt unheard of diſloyalty that can be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to future Ages.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="resolution">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41188:7"/>
            <head>WILTSHIRE'S Reſolution, preſented with the Contributions of divers Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to His MAjESTIES Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at <hi>OXFORD,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as we whoſe names are hereto ſubſcribed, having taken the late Proteſtation recommended unto this Kingdome in generall, according to the direction of both Houſes of Parliament, with His Majeſties conſent, whereby wee hold our ſelves moſt eſpecially bound and engaged to defend, and maintaine with our lives and fortunes according to our utmoſt abilities, the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eſtabliſhed by authority of divers paſt Parliaments ſince the Reformation, and alſo His Majeſties Royall Perſon, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, the juſt and ancient Priviledges of Parliaments, the Lawes of this Land, and the Liberty of the Subject. And whereas it is evident unto us, that at this preſent by the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious practiſes of ſome dangerous ſpirits, the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion hath received manifeſt detriment by calumniating, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing, and impriſoning divers painfull, reverend, and orthodoxe Divines, as namely <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Featley, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Oldſworth, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shute</hi> of London, and many other men of approved ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Doctrine, and unſpotted integrity in their lives and converſations, and almoſt in all places obtruding ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall, Browniſticall, and Schiſmaticall Teachers of falſhood, and rebellion, to the diſhonour of God, and ſcandall of the Pulpit, abuſed nowadayes to ſeduce us from the Loyalty and piety which made our Fore-fathers, and our ſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly happy, and to engage us in a Civill warre one againſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41188:8"/>another. The much, and much worthy to be reverenced Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, and Common Prayer of our Church growne infamous, and a reproach to thoſe that uſe it, and all poſsible endeavour uſed utterly to expunge it.</p>
            <p>And having beene bold with God in his worſhip, no wonder if they proceed to the injury of his Vicegerent, our moſt Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraigne, who oppoſing as much as in him lay, thoſe, and other unjuſt and illegall proceedings, was by their ſubriltie ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſuſpected to His Subjects of inclining to Popery, and many other matters equally falſe; that under ſuch hatefull jealouſies, He might by degrees become leſſe beloved of His Subjects, and they brought into the condition they are at this time in open warre againſt him, wherein, leſt they ſhould relent, they are made beleeve it is for the ſafety, and defence of His Perſon; the moſt abſurd gullery that ever was put upon a Nation.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>KING</hi> did not alone diſlike theſe injuries done to God and Himſelfe, ſo neither alone does Hee ſuffer; for with him moſt of the moſt Learned, and judicious Members of both Houſes, whoſe Nobleneſſe, Honour, Vertues, Piety, Religion, and cleare underſtandings, made them declare themſelves averſe to the preſent courſe of the times, have beene either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned or ſtigmatized with the brand of Traytors, and Papiſts, or at the leaſt malignants, and Prelatiſts: theſe and ſuch like have beene all the Priviledges of Parliaments allowed the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of our times, and worſe is hatching for them if the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence preſerve them not.</p>
            <p>Are our ancient Lawes in any better condition, or ſeeme they not as dead as their prudent contrivers? do not new borne Votes ſupply their roome, and new borne miſeries attend them? the <hi>KING,</hi> his Wife, and Children, voted &amp; forcibly kept out of all that is due to them, wee are required to be aſsiſting hereto; if not, we ſhall be voted to be plundered, &amp; our goods and eſtates
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41188:8"/>ſequeſtred, and all this is pretended to be for the Liberty of the Subject: we have liberty indeed to give, but no liberty to deny: and we muſt give not as we know we are able, but as they think fit, and this they have the impudence to publiſh.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being taken into our ſerious conſideration, and the times now requiring us to declare our ſelves, ſince we can no longer be at peace: firſt condoling the generall calamity of our ſelves, and Ireland, we profeſſe to all the world, that we cannot ſee or find any other lawfull way to free us from the diſtreſſes we are in, then by our beſt aſsiſtance of His Sacred Majeſtie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that ſhall oppoſe Him in an aſſured confidence that His purpoſe is as He hath declared, and no other, than to maintaine and eſtabliſh the Protestant Religion, as it hath beene in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; uſe in this Kingdome ever ſince <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, &amp; likewiſe His own juſt and true prerogative, and inheritance, derived unto Him from His Anceſtours Kings, and Queens of England, and alſo the rights and priviledges of Parliaments, that have beene alway juſtly due to them; to whom we conceive His Majeſty ought eſpecially to hearken, as hath beene the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of his Royall Predeceſſours, they ſeeking in all humility His aſſent to their debates and reſolutions, by reaſon, not by force; and alſo the ancient Lawes of this Kingdome, and all other Acts of Parliament, ratified by the Kings conſent. And laſtly, the Liberty and Property of the Subject: Hereto we hold our ſelves bound by Conſcience and vow to God, Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to our King, and duty to our Country: and ſo God proſper us as wee ſhall be aſsiſting to His Majeſtie in the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all this.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41188:9"/>
            <head>His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> Letter to both Houſes of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> the <hi>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of Ianuary. <hi>1641.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS Majeſty perceiving the manifold diſtractions which now are in this Kingdome, which cannot but bring great inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, and miſchief to this whole Government; In which, as His Majeſty is moſt chiefly intereſſed, ſo Hee holds himſelfe by many reaſons, moſt obliged to do what in Him lies for the preventing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; Though He might juſtly expect (as moſt proper for the duty of Subjects) that propoſitions for the remedies of theſe evils ought rather to come to Him, then from him; yet His Fatherly care of all His people being ſuch, that He will rather lay by any particular reſpect of his owne dignity, then that any time ſhould be loſt for prevention of theſe threatning evils, which cannot admit the delaies of the ordinary proceedings in Parliament, doth thinke fit to make theſe enſuing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>That they will with all ſpeed fall into ſerious conſideration of all thoſe particulars, which they ſhall hold neceſſary, as well for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and maintaining of His Majeſties juſt and Legall Authority, and for the ſettling of His Revenue, as for the preſent and future eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of their priviledges, the free and quiet enjoying of their Eſtates and Fortunes, the liberties of their Perſons, the ſecurity of the true Religion now profeſſed in the Church of England, and the ſettling of Ceremonies in ſuch a manner, as may take away all juſt offence; which when they ſhall have digeſted, and compoſed into one entire body, that ſo His Majeſtie, and themſelves may be able to make the more cleare judgement of them, it ſhall then appeare by what His Majeſty ſhall do, how farre He hath beene from intending, or deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any of thoſe things, which the too great feares and jealouſies of ſome perſons ſeeme to apprehend: And how ready Hee will be to equall and exceed the greateſt examples of the moſt indulgent Princes in their Acts of Grace, and Favour to their people.</p>
            <p>So that if all theſe preſent diſtractions (which ſo apparently threaten the ruine of this Kingdome) do not (by the bleſſing of Almighty God) end in an happy and bleſſed Accommodation; His Majeſty will then be ready to call Heaven and Earth, God and Man to witneſſe, that it hath not failed on His part.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41188:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
